We pick up today on דף ל"ט, daf lamed tes, ארבעים חסר
אחת, arba'im chaser achas, but we start, we are at the bottom
of ל"ח עמוד ב' lamed ches amud bais and we are in
the middle of the question about which things apply in ארץ ישראל
eretz yisroel and in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz,
and what actually we're at the top of ל"ט עמוד א', lamed
tes amud aleph, but maybe we'll pick up again from the bottom
of ל"ח עמוד ב' lamed ches amud bais to give us to
begin the issue again. We have the משנה mishna in ערלה orlah
that teaches
that חדש chadash is אסור מן התורה assur min hatorah everywhere, the
position in Rabbi Eliezer. We've discussed that issue and how we
פסקן, pasken, and
how we פסקן pasken in a very relevant question for חדש chadash
in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but then it said ערלה orlah is
הלכה halacha and כלאים kilayim is דברי סופרים divrei soferim דרבנן. derabbanan.
So what does הלכה halacha mean? So one opinion says that הלכה
halacha meant רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הלכות המדינה,
hilchos hamedina, which might just mean like adopted practice or at most
דרבנן. derabbanan. The other approach is הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai,
which would give it mean weightier than a דרבנן. derabbanan. So now
the argument is going to be to show that it is weightier,
that ערלה orlah is weightier than כלאים, kilayim, so it's weightier than
a דרבנן. derabbanan. כלאים kilayim is דברי סופרים. divrei soferim. And it's
going to be shown by two הלכות, halachos, by how the issue
of ספק sofek plays out in the case of ערלה orlah and
the issue of ספק sofek plays out in the case of כלאים.
kilayim. So let's take a look. So we'll pick up again from
we'll redo this from like eight lines from the bottom on ל"ח
עמוד
ב'.
lamed ches
amud bais. אמר ליה לרב יהודה, amar leh le-Rav Yehuda, עולא Ulla
said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, בשלמא לדידי, bishlama ledidi, line starting
with the word לדידי, ledidi, that's about I think maybe eight lines
from the bottom, בשלמא לדידי bishlama ledidi דאמינא הלכה למשה מסיני, de'amina
halacha lemoshe misinai, if I say ערלה orlah is הלכה למשה מסיני,
halacha lemoshe misinai, היינו דשנינן בין ספק ערלה לספק כלאים, haynu deshaninan
bein sofek orlah lesofek kilayim, I can explain the way the משנה
mishna distinguishes between the between a doubtful ערלה orlah and doubtful כלאים,
kilayim, that we're more lenient by doubtful כלאים kilayim than by doubtful
ערלה, orlah, because ערלה orlah is הלכה למשה מסיני halacha lemoshe misinai
and כלאים kilayim is דרבנן. derabbanan. דתנן, detnan, what do we teach
in the משנה? mishna? ספק ערלה, sofek orlah, if you have a
doubt whether something is ערלה, orlah, בארץ, ba'aretz, in the land of
Israel, אסור, assur, because ארץ eretz דאורייתא, doraissa, בסוריא, bisurya, in the
lands near Israel that David conquered,
מותר, mutar, it's permissible there, it's דרבנן, derabbanan, but בחוץ לארץ, be-chutz
la'aretz, in even more distant חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, it's even more
lenient. What's the greater lenience by ערלה? orlah? יורד ולוקח, yored velokeach,
you can go down into the orchard and purchase from the seller
there, even though you know that there are ערלה orlah trees there,
ובלבד שלא יראנו לוקט, ubilvad shelo yir'enu loket, as long as you
don't see him directly picking from the actual ערלה orlah itself. So
you could know there are ערלה orlah trees, and actually it might
even be that you could even know that the whole, I mean
this would be an extreme read, the whole fruit is ערלה, orlah,
but if you didn't see him pick, well I don't know, maybe
he got from a different orchard and he's just selling it here.
So you know, so that seems already a very very extreme version
of of like of you know the tiniest little ספק sofek suffices.
Okay? As long as it's not blatant in your eyes and you
saw him do it.
How you don't even have to ask.
Right, and you don't have to ask. Now how much more lenient
could you be? So let's keep on reading. ואילו גבי כלאים תנן,
ve-ilu gabei kilayim tnan, but when it comes to כלאים kilayim we
teach in the same משנה, mishna, כרם שנטוע ירק וירק הנמכר חוצה
לו, kerem she-natu yerek ve-yerek hanimkar chutz lo,
if you have a vineyard that has vegetables planted nearby so the
vegetables would be כלאים, kilayim, and there's a little vegetable stand right
near selling the same vegetables, selling like broccoli or whatever it's selling,
like cucumbers, okay. בארץ אסור, ba'aretz assur, in ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael
it's forbidden, בסוריא מותר, bisurya mutar, in סוריא surya it's permissible.
That itself enough of a ספק. sofek. Alright, selling cucumbers near a
vineyard that has cucumbers planted nearby, but who knows where the cucumbers
came from, you know. בחוץ לארץ, be-chutz la'aretz, but in חוץ לארץ
chutz la'aretz it's even more lenient. How lenient? יורד ולוקט, yored veloket,
you can actually see him picking the cucumbers from the vineyard
that they're grown in. So it's not even really
a ספק. sofek. The הלכה halacha of כלאים kilayim in חוץ לארץ
chutz la'aretz is as long as you're not the one that picks
it, you can actually buy it. So it doesn't even have to
be a ספק sofek or grows it, right. And רש"י Rashi says
that if you look at the רש"י Rashi at the top of
ל"ט עמוד א', lamed tes amud aleph, רש"י Rashi says just the
second line, we'll take it from the middle of a רש"י, Rashi,
דלא אסרו בחוץ לארץ אלא את הזורע או את הלוקט בידיים. delo
assru be-chutz la'aretz ela es hazoreya o es haloket beyadayim.
The only person, the only one who's forbidden to eat ערלה orlah
is if you were the one who planted the ערלה, orlah, I
mean כלאים, kilayim, excuse me, if you're the one who planted the
כלאים kilayim or the one who picks it. So it's not even
really a ספק, sofek, it's a ודאי, vaday, but as long as
you didn't do it yourself. Okay, so anyway, extreme קולות kulas by
ערלה orlah and כלאים, kilayim, but כלאים kilayim is even more lenient,
you can even see it being picked. So he says I can
understand. One's הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, one's דרבנן. derabbanan. But
according to you they should be at the same level. אלא לדידך
ela ledidach that you say that they're both דרבנן, derabbanan, ניתני nisni
top of ל"ט עמוד א', lamed tes amud aleph, תני או זה
וזה יורד וילקוט, tnei o zeh ve-zeh yored ve-yilkot, to have the
same הלכה, halacha,
either both of them. goes you can buy as long as you
don't see it being picked in your presence. או זה וזה יורד
ולוקח, O zeh vezeh yored velokeiach, or in both of those you
can see it being picked in your presence, as long as you're
not the one to pick it. But why in one case can
you see it being picked and in the other case not, if
they're one, if they're both at the same level? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר ליה שמואל לרבננא, Amar lei Shmuel l'Rabanana, so you
know what? You're right. Because שמואל Shmuel who is the one who
teaches in the name of, who is the one who taught that
it was הלכות המדינה, Hilchos HaMedina, who taught that it was דרבנן,
D'rabbanan, that ערלה Orlah was דרבנן, D'rabbanan, he told to רבננא, Rabanana,
תני או זה וזה יורד ולוקח. Tani o zeh vezeh yored velokeiach.
He actually told him to פסקן pasken the same way for both
of those. Okay? You have to switch the גירסא girsa of the
משנה Mishna to have the משנה Mishna either read in both of
those it's okay if somebody picks it as long as it's not
picked in your presence, or another version is teach for both of
those you can even have it picked in your presence as long
as you don't pick it. Okay? So the answer, the question is
according to you, שמואל, Shmuel, they're both דרבנן, D'rabbanan, why are there
different הלכות? halachos? And the answer is you're right, they're not different
הלכות. halachos. We'll switch the משנה Mishna to have it say that
it's the same הלכה halacha for both. Okay? But according to the
other approach, no, and they're both extremely lenient, but כלאים Kilayim is
even more lenient. ערלה Orlah you can, you can't see it being
picked, and כלאים Kilayim you can even see it being picked. Yes,
Michael?
So is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael would we say this אסור assur
for non-Jew to זורע כלאים zorei'a Kilayim or just for Jews?
I mean, whether a non-Jew is עובר over on the שבע מצוות
בני נח Sheva Mitzvos Bnei Noach or does the כלאים Kilayim become
אסור assur for us?
Well, פה, poh, I mean like שבע מצוות בני נח, Sheva Mitzvos
Bnei Noach, it's not one of them, but you know, for instance,
you know, question about like שמיטה Shmitta and all that,
so non-Jews have no שייכות shaychus to כלאים. Kilayim.
Well, we're going to see later they are אסור assur in like
הרכבת אילן harkavas ha'ilan and so on, but a normal כלאים, Kilayim,
it's not אסור assur for them to do wherever they're doing it.
In terms of it becoming אסור assur for Jews, the answer is
that it would, if it's, but that, so if they do plant
it, I mean yes, so that, but then we'll get into that.
If it's אסור assur for them, how come it says you can
see him picking it and then?
Because that's חוצה לארץ Chutz L'Aretz הלכה. halacha. In חוצה לארץ Chutz
L'Aretz it's just extremely lenient.
But you're
asking about in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Okay, and if a Jewish person did it in חוצה לארץ, Chutz
L'Aretz, another couldn't eat it if he had eaten?
No, it has nothing to do with if the person was עובר
over or not. It does just have to do with the way
in which they made the food אסור. assur. If you planted, you
go ahead and you, and you don't care about this הלכה halacha
or whether you don't know any better and you go ahead and
you plant כלאים, Kilayim, okay, then you're אסור assur to eat it,
but then I can go ahead, I mean okay, we could talk
about מסייע ידי עוברי עבירה, msayei'a yedei ovrei aveira, but let's bracket
that for a moment. If I went ahead and I bought it
from you or even if I saw you pick it off the
tree and I bought it from you as long as I'm not
the one who planted it, I could go ahead and eat it.
All right? It doesn't have to do with Jew versus non-Jew here.
Interesting because like שמיטה Shmitta for instance, the fruit itself...
I understand, but particularly here in חוצה לארץ Chutz L'Aretz we're very
lenient. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So that
מר בריה דרבינא Mar brei d'Ravina מתני לה לקולא. matni lah l'kula.
זה וזה יורד ולוקח. Zeh vezeh yored velokeiach. מר בריה דרבינא Mar
brei d'Ravina approved, said that was lenient and said in both cases
you could actually see the person pick, ובלבד שלא ילקט בידו, ubilvad
shelo yilkat beyado, as long as you don't pick directly. Which presumably
means he was also following שמואל's Shmuel approach, the understanding them to
be at the same level and understanding ערלה Orlah to also be
דרבנן. D'rabbanan. And if they're both דרבנן, D'rabbanan, you might as well
make them both equally as lenient. And as long as you don't
pick it directly, you're okay. Okay, אמר ליה שבי לשמואל, Amar lei
Shivi l'Shmuel, Shivi said to שמואל—remember Shmuel שמואל's Shmuel the one who
taught that they were both דרבנן D'rabbanan at the same
level—אריוך, Aryoch, אריוך Aryoch like a tall one, ספק לי ואנא
איכול.
Sfeik li v'ana
eichol.
Is that from אריה Aryeh like in אריה? Aryeh?
Or I don't know how it's pronounced,
אריוך. Aryoch. I'm going to guess that's how it's pronounced. How is
it translated?
אריוך Aryoch was a long roots.
I think he's calling שמואל, Shmuel, what's the translation? Sic. S-I-C. We
have a note.
It doesn't translate, but he wants you to read it.
No, I don't want you to read it. I want you to
read it yourself and then summarize.
They think it might be like king or a lion.
Oh, lion.
That's why אריוך מלך אלסר.
Aryoch melech Elasar.
That's true. Oh, that's true. All right, interesting, interesting. I was assuming
it came from ארוך. aroch. Okay, anyway, ספק לי ואנא איכול. Sfeik
li v'ana eichol. You make it a ספק safek for me and
I'll eat it. Okay? So what that means is רש"י Rashi says,
just pick not in my presence. Okay, but pick not in my
presence make it a ספק safek for me means that we're going
the, remember that sounds like a big leniency but it really is
the stricter of the two options, right? The stricter of the two
options is you can't see it being picked. The more lenient one
is you can see it being picked as long as you don't
pick it yourself. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says ספק לי לקוץ שלא בפני שיספק אצלי ואנא איכול ובערלה קאי.
Sfeik li likot shelo bifnai sheyisafek etzli v'ana eichol uv'Orlah ka'i. So
this is actually adopting the, at least by the, you know, not
changing the משנה Mishna and at least by the משנה Mishna by
ערלה Orlah keeping it that you're not allowed to see it being
picked. You go ahead and you pick for me, okay, I won't,
I won't go ahead and eat it. So Michael, you asked before
is there an איסור issur of כלאים, Kilayim, every, if you plant
an orchard, I know, I'm saying if you plant an orchard, you're
always going to be dealing with ערלה. Orlah. So here's a way
of dealing with ערלה Orlah in חוצה לארץ. Chutz L'Aretz. Right? I
didn't do anything wrong. I just planted my apple orchard. It's now
everything is in the third year. You want to buy it from
me. We're both two פרום frum Jews. I'll just pick and sell
it to you and you just won't be around when I do
the picking. Okay, so basically he tells
him when to do that. Yeah, exactly. He says, are you? Like,
you have any idea what to tell?
I don't know. Okay, anyway, רב אויא ורבה בר בר חנה Rav
Avya v'Rabba bar Bar Chana מחלפו ספיקי להדדי. machalifu sefeika l'hadadi. They
basically, sort of like you know how these אמוראים Amoraim would exchange
משלוח מנות, mishloach manot, so they would basically say like, I'll tell
you what, I'll go, I'm going to go pick and sell it
to you, and then you go pick and you sell it to
me. Whatever, I don't know if they, if each of them had
an orchard or they were whatever. Anyway, they helped each other out.
So, okay, to do it. So you can do a lot of
tricks. Okay. הני חריפי דפומבדיתא, Hanei charifei d'Pumbedita, so the sharp ones
of פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, רש"י Rashi tells you that that's האיפא ורמיבי, Ha'eifa
u'Ramibi, the sons of רחבה. Rechava. Anyway, those, they were called the
sharp ones of פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. אין ערלה בחוצה לארץ. Ein orlah b'Chutz
La'aretz. While we're sort of heading there, okay, there's no ערלה בחוצה
לארץ orlah b'Chutz La'aretz as opposed to just like, well, as long
as you don't see it being picked, they made a much more
blanket statement: ah, come on, it doesn't apply. Okay, so you know
when you start being so lenient, you're going to lead to somebody
saying something like this. So anyway,
so שלח רב יהודה לקמיה דרבי יוחנן. shlach Rav Yehuda l'kamei d'Rabbi
Yochanan. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda sent to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, hey,
you know these, these אמוראים Amoraim here in פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, you know
the sharp ones of פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, they're saying ערלה orlah doesn't apply
at all in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. So, and he's in, and
he's in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. שלח ליה, Shlach lei, so רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan sent back to him, you might reasonably expect that
somebody in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is going to be more protective
of the איסורים issurim of ערלה orlah and so on. So he
sent back to him,
שלח ליה, shlach lei, סתום ספיקא, setom sefeika, sort of silence the
ספק. safek. רש"י Rashi says like prevent, that now that the people
are being so lenient about this and saying that it doesn't apply
at all, you should stop telling people that you can be lenient
in a case of ספק. safek. Like it would become, it became
a slippery slope. So now that people are basically saying it doesn't
apply at all, you need to stop, stop, silence the situations of
ספק, safek, stop teaching people about that ספק safek you can be
lenient around. ואבד ודאה, v'abeid vadah, get rid of everything that's a
ודאי vaday ערלה, orlah, destroy it. והכרז על
פירותיהן שטעונין גניזה, v'hachreiz al peiroteihen she-te'unin genizah, and announce over their
fruit that they maybe did this trick, you know, either they didn't
care at all or maybe they did this trick of like you
pick for me and I'll pick for you type of a thing.
So he was sort of taking these like countermeasures
about what he sees as over-lenience and
basically get rid of all their fruit, say that it has to
be buried. וכל אומר אין ערלה בחוצה לארץ, v'chol omer ein orlah
b'Chutz La'aretz, and anybody who says ערלה orlah does not apply in
חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, לא יהיה לו נין ונכד. lo yiheyeh lo
nin v'neched. He should not have a child or whatever, a grandchild
or a descendant משליך חבל בגורל בקהל השם, mashlich chevel b'goral bi-kehal
Hashem, casting his lot with the congregation of השם. Hashem. So pretty
extreme both in terms of the rhetoric and in terms of the
response. Okay, anyway, but this is the slippery slope and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan was responding back. גמרא Gemara says דאינהו כמאן סבירא להו?
d'inhu k'man sevira lehu? So who do they hold like? Because rather
than read it that they just got carried away with all of
these ספק safek tricks, if they're really saying אין ערלה בחוצה לארץ,
ein orlah b'Chutz La'aretz, presumably there is an opinion out there that
they might say that, that it doesn't apply at all. So who
is that opinion? So כי הא דתניא, ki ha d'tanya, like that
which we taught:
רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אומר משום רבי יוסי בן דורמסקא שאמר משום
רבי יוסי הגלילי שאמר משום רבי יוחנן בן נורי שאמר משום רבי
אליעזר הגדול. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yossi omer mishum Rabbi Yossi ben Durmaska
she-amar mishum Rabbi Yossi ha-Gelili she-amar mishum Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri she-amar
mishum Rabbi Eliezer ha-Gadol. So it's a long tradition going back to
רבי אליעזר: Rabbi Eliezer: אין ערלה בחוצה לארץ. ein orlah b'Chutz La'aretz.
It does not apply at all. By the way, if people know,
remember רמב"ם Rambam is of the position that anything that's a הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai is never debated. Whereas here, A, we
have a debate whether it's a הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai,
this idea of ערלה בחוצה לארץ, orlah b'Chutz La'aretz, and B, we
have people saying that it's not even true, that there isn't ערלה
בחוצה לארץ orlah b'Chutz La'aretz as opposed to it exists as a
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. Anyway, okay. גמרא Gemara says ולא?
והאנן תנן רבי אליעזר אומר, v'lo? v'ha'anan tenan Rabbi Eliezer omer, we
taught רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which presumably is the same רבי אליעזר
הגדול, Rabbi Eliezer ha-Gadol, אומר אף החדש, omer af he-chadash, even חדש.
chadash. He's adding to those that said that ערלה orlah and כלאים
kilayim are in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz and he's saying even חדש.
chadash. And here רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying אין ערלה בחוצה
לארץ. ein orlah b'Chutz La'aretz. Pretty big contradiction. And we have this
tradition of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. You could say it's תרי תנאי
אליבא דרבי אליעזר. trei tanna'ei aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer. But let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. תני חדש, tani chadash, take out the word
אף. af. Have the משנה Mishnah read: ערלה orlah and כלאים kilayim
apply in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
no, ערלה orlah and כלאים kilayim don't apply, only חדש chadash applies
in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. Okay, so anyway, but here we at
least we have a tradition in the name of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer that there's no ערלה orlah in חוץ. Chutz. אמר רב אסי
אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan.
That's disputed, apparently.
Because, right, well, yeah, clearly it's disputed. It's our סתם משנה, stam
Mishnah, it's the משנה Mishnah in ערלה, Orlah, right? And here again
we have a teaching of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר רב אסי
אמר רבי יוחנן ערלה בחוצה לארץ הלכה למשה מסיני. amar Rav Assi
amar Rabbi Yochanan orlah b'Chutz La'aretz halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. Again, so here
we have a reiteration of the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai
position again coming from רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, adopting a more מחמיר
machmir position on this. אמר ליה רב זירא לרב אסי, amar lei
Rav Zeira l'Rav Assi, so רב זירא Rav Zeira said to רב
אסי, Rav Assi, והתניא, v'hatanya, how could you say? Okay, this is,
I mean we said yesterday an opinion that it was הלכה למשה
מסיני. Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. But anyway, here’s a question that we didn’t
think to ask until now about that position. והתניא, vehatanya, or should
be והתניא, vehatanya, a משנה Mishnah teaches: ספק ערלה בארץ אסור בסוריא
מותר ובחוץ לארץ יורד ולוקט. Safek Orlah ba’aretz asur, beSurya mutar, uvechutz
la’aretz yored veloket. So how could you have all these leniencies, right,
that it should be, we should be lenient in a ספק? safek?
You can even have somebody, or it should be יורד ולוקח, yored
veloke’ach, actually it should be יורד ולוקח yored veloke’ach
by ערלה, Orlah, right? ארץ ערלה Eretz Orlah is יורד ולוקח. yored
veloke’ach. Anyway, we have all these leniencies that as long as you
don’t see it being picked in front of you, you’re okay. If
it’s הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, how could we be so
lenient? Right, we should be strict at least in certainly the, you
know, in that case of יורד ולוקח. yored veloke’ach. אשתומם
כשעה חדא. Ishtomem kesha'a chada. He was like dumbfounded for a moment,
like he didn’t have a response. Like he, you know, he was,
אמר ליה, amar leih, and then he said אימא כך נאמר. eima
kach ne'emar. He says, you know what, maybe this is how the
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai was said. ספיקא וליתא כך נאמר,
sveika uleisa kach ne'emar, or let us say that כך נאמר, kach
ne'emar, that this was the way the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe
MiSinai was taught. ספיקא מותר ודא אסור. sveika mutar, vada asur. That
the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai incorporated the idea that it’s
מותר mutar in a case of ספק safek and it’s אסור asur
in a case of ודאי. vadai. So this leniency,
well, okay, I don’t know, סוריא Surya would be whatever. I mean,
I mean, you know, סוריא Surya could be an added stringency.
Like, there’s no way that סוריא Surya could be a
הלכה למשה מסיני.
Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai. Right. Well, it could be in a case of
כיבוש יחיד. kibbush yachid. But presumably the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe
MiSinai is all חוץ לארץ. chutz la’aretz. If סוריא Surya is any
more stringent, that was an added דרבנן. d'rabbanan. But anyway, the הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai incorporates this idea of how to handle
a case of ספק. safek. Now I want to say two things
about this. First of all, the very fact again getting to this
idea of הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, here we see it’s
debated. Is it הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai? Is it a
הלכה halacha at all? And here also, notice he said אימא כך
נאמר. eima kach ne’emar. I can say that this was what the
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai was. So it’s not like he
actually had the tradition that that’s what the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
L’Moshe MiSinai was. He was like reconstructing
what, since it’s taught in this case of a ספק, safek, and
I know it’s הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, it must be
that the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai incorporated this idea of
ספק. safek. Right, so it’s like a reconstructing of the הלכה למשה
מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai as opposed to like a clearly remembered unbroken
tradition about it. So that’s just number one. Number two is it
does raise interesting
questions. Oh, someone decided, decided,
oh I see, they are cleaning for פסח Pesach today. Whoa, fancy.
I have a whole green thing here.
Oh, it’s good.
April and
you got gold. Really.
Anyway, שקויח, shkoach, thank you. I don't know why I buy the
Starbucks coffee and it's never as good as getting it from the
store, so I don't know, have to figure out, have to find
out their secret sauce. Okay anyway, thank you.
So the issue about הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, the other
question is, here’s a big question, right? What, we say ספק דאורייתא
לחומרא. safek d'Oraisa l'chumra. Now in general רמב״ם Rambam says, or at
least in general he’s understood, whatever. רמב״ם Rambam says that the principle
that ספק דאורייתא לחומרא safek d'Oraisa l'chumra is a דרבנן d'rabbanan דין.
din. That as far as the תורה Torah is concerned, ספק דאורייתא
לקולא. safek d'Oraisa l'kula. Now that’s funny because this גמרא Gemara doesn’t
sound this way. This גמרא Gemara sounds like he was saying, if
it’s a הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, how could we be
lenient in a case of a ספק? safek? And this is no,
the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai incorporates the idea that we
can be lenient in a case of ספק, safek, which sounds like
the normal presumption would be that anything that harkens back to משה
Moshe and certainly something that’s a דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, the default presumption would
be ספק safek would be a חומרא, chumra, you would be מחמיר.
machmir. And you need a special teaching, a special, you know, caveat
in this case that you can be lenient in a case of
ספק. safek. So it raises an interesting question according to the general
position of רמב״ם. Rambam. But what you could always say is that
maybe what bothers them is not just סתם ספק לקולא stam safek
l’kula like the הלכה Halacha of סוריא. Surya. What bothers them is
how extreme of a ספק safek it is, right, how preposterous of
a ספק safek it is. You got the whole vineyard and as
long as you didn’t see him picking directly, maybe that’s what bothers
them. That’s a crazy, that’s not even really a ספק, safek, that’s
like, you know, that’s a crazy, crazy קולא. kula. What? They manipulated
the ספק safek and how much of a doubt is there anyway?
So it could be that that’s really what’s bothering them. The basic
idea of ספק לקולא safek l’kula maybe wouldn’t have bothered them. And
actually, if memory serves, I think there’s a discussion in the ר״ן
Ran somewhere. It might be the ר״ן, Ran, it might be a
רבינו יונה, Rabbeinu Yona, anyway, about this question about assuming ספק דאורייתא
לחומרא safek d'Oraisa l'chumra is a דאורייתא d'Oraisa דין. din. Is ספק
הלכה למשה מסיני safek Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai לחומרא l’chumra or לקולא? l’kula?
A real ספק, safek, not a manipulated crazy ספק safek like this.
So that’s like an interesting question, right, is part of the weight
of הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L’Moshe MiSinai, even if you believe, even
if you sort of, you know, take it as a, you know,
tradition that goes all the way back to משה, Moshe, but it’s
not like a directly explicitly type of a commanded thing as a
מצוה mitzvah and so on, so does it have that same weight
of ספק לחומרא? safek l'chumra?
Well here you say it’s לקולא, l’kula, based on his answer. Right,
based on his answer,
here you say it’s לקולא. l’kula. Well, no, this one is לקולא.
l’kula. If anything this should make you assume that the default would
be לחומרא, l'chumra, but the reason that this גמרא Gemara is not,
is not evidence one way or the other is because this might
be, this גמרא Gemara is not the סתמא stama idea that ספק
לקולא, safek l'kula, but the manipulating, you know,
fictional ספק safek is לקולא. l'kula. That's the real problem here. Yeah.
What's the mechanism by which something is declared הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha
L'Moshe MiSinai?
Well, according to רמב"ם, Rambam, there's no mechanism, it's just that these
are the traditions that go back, and רמב"ם Rambam claims because,
look—for which we cannot find a פסוק pasuk or whatever.
Well, right, but that's what makes it הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai and not דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, is that it's an oral tradition. Well,
how's that happen? It happens by a passed down tradition. Look, רמב"ם
Rambam says that what do you call it, that for רמב"ם Rambam
it was very important because he was dealing—I'm only going to spend
one minute on this because we got to get back—but he was
dealing with the whole Karaites challenge about how can you guys say
that we're supposed to believe your תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al peh,
your traditions, if you argue about everything? Okay, so therefore it clearly
shows that your traditions are faulty. So and if you can't, if
you don't have any consensus around any type of a thing, then
clearly then clearly the whole tradition is in ספק. safek. So the
רמב"ם's Rambam answer to it was that basically the reason of all
those debates is because very little was actually directly handed down. Basically
we just got the פסוקים, pesukim, we got the תורה, Torah, and
we got some hermeneutic principles, you know, an understanding of how we
can interpret it, and from there we just applied our human intellect
and that led to all the debates. So the debate doesn't signal
a break in the מסורה masorah because actually there never was a
מסורה masorah about the actual bottom line הלכות. halachos. The fundamental 99%
of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh is our interpretation of it,
our being empowered to interpret it. But he says but the one
area where there was actually a מסורה masorah is הלכה למשה מסיני.
Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. There actually the actual law has been passed down,
and there it was necessary for him to say, oh and there
there was never a מחלוקת. machlokes. The problem is that there was
a מחלוקת machlokes as we've seen right now. Okay, but according to
רמב"ם Rambam anyway, he would say, you know, that's just a small
number of traditions that go all the way back. Now, I do
want to say that this is somewhat questioned because, you know, there
are places where the גמרא Gemara uses the phrase הלכה למשה מסיני
Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai like a משנה ידיים Mishnah Yadayim rhetorically, where it's
clearly talking about a דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. Actually it's also about like מעשר
עני Ma'aser Ani on שמיטה Shmita in the lands outside of ישראל,
Yisrael, עמון ומואב, Ammon u-Moav, anyway, and it's used—it says הלכה למשה
מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai which
just means like it's a long tradition, but clearly it cannot be
a הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. And the ראש Rosh says
that explicitly. So there's some discussion among scholars, you know, whatever, which
is when do we assume הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai means
it literal, or when do we assume that it's meant rhetorically? Sometimes
in the גמרא, Gemara, for example, when the גמרא Gemara says
הלכתא, hilchasa, רש"י—not Rashi הלכתא hilchasa after a debate, but like a,
you know, הלכה halacha or הלכתא hilchasa about a particular law—רש"י Rashi
says that that means הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, but the
נצי"ב Netziv discusses in his introduction to the שאילתות, She'iltos, I think
that's where he discusses it, that he points out that certain ראשונים,
Rishonim, I think רמב"ם Rambam as well, anyway, don't read it like
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai and understand that that הלכתא hilchasa
in those cases means like it's an ancient tradition, but that we
forgot the—it's like an ancient דרבנן d'Rabbanan that we forgot the reason
for, but we're not and but we're not claiming that it goes
all the way back to משה. Moshe. Okay, but that's when it
just says הלכתא. hilchasa. When it says הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai, it's generally understood to mean literal, but there are some who
say that no, sometimes it's rhetorical. There's Christine Hayes has a nice
article on it. Yes.
But the phrase הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai does not predate
רמב"ם?
Rambam?
What do you mean? The phrase הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai
is in the גמרא Gemara all the time.
רמב"ם Rambam just says, רמב"ם Rambam just says that, a, he lists
like the total number of things that are הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
L'Moshe MiSinai in the גמרא, Gemara, like thirty-some-odd things, and he says
that they were never debated. Yeah. I thought for רמב"ם Rambam in
the beginning of משנה תורה Mishneh Torah talks about the pristine historical
time before things were forgotten when there was no מחלוקת, machlokes, and
a מחלוקת machlokes is a corruption rather than a positive—But
it's not a corruption of a tradition. There was no מחלוקת machlokes
because if everybody was at the same intellectual level and the and
they were all always in the same body, so and they could
decide every debate, then there would always be consensus because every debate
would be decided and everybody at the same level arrived at the
same conclusion. It's not a corruption of a tradition. It's the fact
that we're human beings—right, it's the fact that we're human beings and
that we don't and we're not all sitting together and coming to
a single decision, and we have different levels of intellect and different
types of things, and therefore we come up with different ways of
reading the same פסוק. pasuk. But it's not a corruption of the
tradition.
It's a lack of living in an ideal world, but it's not
a corruption of the tradition.
Are you suggesting we're not living in an ideal world?
Correct. Okay. All right, moving on. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Anyway, you see right here it says הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
L'Moshe MiSinai. Okay, כך נאמר, Kach ne'emar, כך נאמר, kach ne'emar, this
was what the הלכה halacha was. ספק מותר וודאי אסור. Safek mutar
v'vadai assur. The stuff— The ספק safek is permissible, the ודאי vaday
is of forbidden and presumably even a manipulated fictional ספק. safek. אמר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. Another teaching in
the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Again remember רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan here is the stronger position on all of this. לוקין על
כלאים דבר תורה. Lokin al kilayim de-var Torah. You get lashes for
כלאים kilayim presumably in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael from you know as
a תורה Torah matter. אמר ליה רבי אלעזר בר רבי יוסי והנן
תנן הכלאים מדברי סופרים. Amar lei Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yosi ve-hanan
tnan ha-kilayim mi-divrei sofrim. So no, it's he understood that he means
you don't have to say that you get lashes in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, he understood that you mean you get lashes you know
out of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, so first רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says that ערלה orlah is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai.
Then he says that כלאים kilayim what until now everybody has said
is דברי סופרים, divrei sofrim, he is saying you get lashes on.
He said how could you say that? והנן תנן הכלאים מדברי סופרים.
Ve-hanan tnan ha-kilayim mi-divrei sofrim. לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's not difficult.
כאן בכלאי כרם כאן בהרכבה. Kan be-kil'ei kerem kan be-harkava. The difference
is כלאים kilayim of seeds or plant or actual like a type
of a grafting onto a tree. בהרכבת אילן כשמואל. Be-harkavat ilan ki-Shmuel.
Why? Cause a grafting on a tree although it is land-based is
we're going to see more similar to a type of a crossbreeding
of animals. It's like actually taking the physical thing, not just putting
things together and then letting them grow, okay? It's actually taking and
you know, I mean although it's true the physical animals also you're
letting them grow but there's more of a direct physical manipulation of
like, you know, of the thing itself.
So
הרכבה harkava is worse.
הרכבה Harkava is worse and הרכבה harkava you get lashes even in
חוצה. chutza. It's not considered תלוי בארץ. taluy ba-aretz. כשמואל, Ki-Shmuel, like
שמואל Shmuel teaches. דאמר
שמואל De-amar Shmuel yeah yeah yeah would not talking about the איסור
אכילה issur achila we're talking correct. כשמואל Ki-Shmuel like שמואל Shmuel teaches
דאמר שמואל את חוקותי תשמורו, de-amar Shmuel et chukotai tishmoru, you should
observe my edicts. חוקים שחקקתי לך כבר. Chukim she-chakakti lecha kvar. Doesn't
say תשמורו את חוקותי tishmoru et chukotai but את חוקותי תשמורו. et
chukotai tishmoru. So the חוקות chukot are ancient. Okay, and what's the
next פסוק? pasuk? בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים שדך לא תזרע כלאים. Behemtecha
lo tarbia kilayim sadecha lo tizra kilayim. Now we learn using another
גמרא Gemara that fact that they are seen as ancient to say
that they are part of the שבע מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvot
benei Noach. They pre-existed, they existed before this פסוק pasuk was stated.
They went all the way back to בני נח. benei Noach. Even
בני נח benei Noach are אסור assur on שבע מצוות בני נח?
sheva mitzvot benei Noach?
It is according to this opinion. Okay and I think that's how
the רמב"ם פוסק. Rambam posek. Okay that even בני נח benei Noach
are אסור assur in הרכבת אילן harkavat ilan and in crossbreeding בהמה.
behema. You obviously are other slices quickly pull up how רמב"ם פוסק
Rambam posek about this. שבע מצוות בני נח? Sheva mitzvot benei Noach?
What?
It's it's the plus.
What? Yeah, exactly. Okay.
Hold on, let me see if I can pick it up.
He thinks it's a weirdest thing that it's אסור assur to do
but the juice that you can use, I think this is a
weird thing.
There's lots of things like that, it's
delicious, I can make a ברכה bracha on the, but we would
be
we would be eating very little fruit if that were not the
case.
Why do you say that? Most fruit is from grafted.
Okay. Anyway I'm not going to find it right away. But anyway,
all right moving on. Let's go on. חבר'ה, Chevre, let's go on.
Okay anyway, so so it says anyway,
the first thing we learn from this is at least according to
this position, might be we don't פוסק posek this way, but according
to this position בני נח benei Noach are אסור assur on crossbreeding
animals and on grafting trees. בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים שדך לא תזרע
כלאים. Behemtecha lo tarbia kilayim sadecha lo tizra kilayim. And now we
say the following: מה בהמתך בהרבעה אף שדך בהרכבה. Mah behemtecha be-harva'ah
af sadecha be-harkavah.
So first of all to understand what are we talking about when
we're saying that these are ancient and go all the way back?
We're not talking about just planting seeds although this says לא תזרע
lo tizra seed. But we're talking about something similar like manipulating a
big physical object, okay and bringing them together. So that would be
a grafting of a tree. ומה בהמתך נוהג בין בארץ בין בחוצה
לארץ אף שדך נוהג בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ. U-mah behemtecha noheg
bein ba-aretz bein be-chutza la-aretz af sadecha noheg bein ba-aretz bein be-chutza
la-aretz. And another thing we learn from this, once we've established we're
talking about grafting, is that the same way the animal crossbreeding applies
outside of Israel אף שדך נוהג בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ. af
sadecha noheg bein ba-aretz bein be-chutza la-aretz. Even the field okay you
you know even the case of what do you call it of
grafting applies outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and you would actually
biblically be prohibited and get lashes. Okay at least according to רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. והא כתיב שדך, Ve-ha ketiv sadecha, but it says
שדך. sadecha.
And apparently the question here, you could say the question is that
שדך sadecha doesn't sound like we're talking about an orchard, but the
question רש"י Rashi says is that שדך sadecha is possessive. Your field,
which suggests the idea in your land, in the land of Israel,
and not that it would apply outside of Israel. So he says
ההוא למעוטי זרעים שבחוץ. Hahu le-ma'uti zera'im she-ba-chutz. He says there are
two things going on in the פסוק. pasuk. They're sort of like
the פשט pshat level.
שדך לא תזרע כלאים, Sadecha lo tizra kilayim, which is seeds. So
כלאים kilayim of seeds like a planting seeds, that is only in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. That's שדך sadecha and not שדה חוץ לארץ.
sadeh chutz la-aretz. Okay however, there's another level of the פסוק, pasuk,
the דרש drash level, which is reading this similar to to the
crossbreeding of animals and then we'd be talking about grafting trees and
that applies in חוצה לארץ. chutz la-aretz. So the דרש drash level
grafting trees applies in חוצה לארץ chutz la-aretz and you even get
lashes according to this, the פשט pshat level of seeds, that's the
תזרע tizra and that's the שדך sadecha and that's only
in. No no
we're reading שדך *Sadchecha* only in terms of what do you call
it only in terms of to exclude the חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz
*Chutz La'aretz*.
So you can't employ me to do it and I can't do
it.
Correct. Okay. By the way, if you just want to see how
רמב"ם Rambam, *Rambam* פוסק paskens *Paskins* about this. כלאי אילנות הרי הם
בכלל מה שנאמר שדך לא תזרע כלאים sadcha lo tizra kilayim, *Kilay
Ilanos harei heim bechlall mah shene'emar sadcha lo tizra kilayim* המרכיב אילן
באילן *hamarkiv ilan be'ilan* שהרכיב ייחור *she'hirkiv yichur* etc. etc. הרי זה
לוקה מן התורה בכל מקום בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ *harei zeh
lokei min ha'Torah bechol makom bein ba'aretz bein bechutz la'aretz*. So רמב"ם
Rambam *Rambam* פוסק pasken *Paskins* like רב Rav יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* okay
although I'm not sure if he פוסק *Paskins* that it applies to
בני נח *Bnei Noach* but he does פוסק *Paskin* that it applies
in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz? *Chutz La'aretz* and you get מלקות *Malkus*.
Now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this.
This רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is very beautiful. חוצה לארץ לא חסמו לכם
מן השמים *Chutza La'aretz
lo chasmu lachem min hashomayim*. Right. Very beautiful. Yep. Okay. רב חנן
ורב ענן הוו שקלי ואזלי באורחא *Rav Chanan ve'Rav Anan havuhu shakli
ve'azli be'orcha*. רב חנן *Rav Chanan* and רב ענן *Rav Anan* were
walking on the road. חזיו לההוא גברא דקא זרע זרועין בהדי הדדי
*Chazyu le'hahu gavra de'ka zara zeruin behadi hadadi*. He saw a person,
this was in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz *Chutz La'aretz*, planting seeds together.
אמר ליה *Amar lei* so I don't know who said to whom
but anyway רב ענן *Rav Anan* presumably said to רב חנן *Rav
Chanan* נייתי מר נשמתיה *Neisei mar nishmasei* let's go put him in
חרם cherem. *Cherem* because he's being עובר *Over* on this הלכה halacha,
*Halacha* he's planting כלאים kilayim *Kilayim* in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz, *Chutz
La'aretz*. So אמר ליה *Amar lei* because until now, right, we were
talking about buying the כלאים kilayim *Kilayim* and
closing your eyes and creating a ספק safek *Safek*. But you're not
allowed to do it. That's what's so we should go put him
in חרם *Cherem*. אמר ליה לא חביר סו *Amar lei lo chavir
su*. Yeah it's not clear to you exactly what the הלכה *Halacha*
is. The fact that you're saying that shows you don't really understand
the הלכה *Halacha*. Okay that was a curious response. וטו *Vetu* we're
not done. חזיו לההוא גברא דקא זרע חטי ושערי בי גופני *Chazyu
le'hahu gavra de'ka zara chitti ushari bei gufni*. They saw a man
planting wheat and barley in a vineyard. אמר ליה *Amar lei* they
said and נייתי מר נשמתיה *Neisei mar nishmasei* go let's go put
him in חרם *Cherem*. The master, the master should put him in
חרם *Cherem*. אמר ליה לא צהיר תו *Amar lei lo tzahiri tu*.
It's not clear to you what the הלכה *Halacha* is. So could
you please explain this riddle? So then the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says
לא קיימא לן כרבי יאשיה *Lo kayma lan ke'Rabbi Yoshiya*? Don't we
hold like רבי יאשיה Rebbe Yoshiyah *Rabbi Yoshiya*? What does רבי יאשיה
*Rabbi Yoshiya* say? דאמר עד שיזרע חטה ושעורה וחרצן במפולת יד *De'amar
ad she'yizra chittah u'se'orah ve'chartzan be'mapoles yad*. רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshiya* says
a person does not transgress planting כלאים kilayim *Kilayim* unless they plant
wheat, barley, and a grape seed all at the same time. So
even planting wheat and barley in an existing vineyard would not be
the prohibition of planting כלאים kilayim *Kilayim* according to him.
Just in
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz, *Chutz La'aretz*?
Well okay so that's a question like are we just lenient in
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz. *Chutz La'aretz* how does this חוץ לארץ chutz
la'aretz. *Chutz La'aretz* aspect apply to it? But he's saying at least
at least in the חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz, *Chutz La'aretz* context don't
go and have a don't go and have a fit here okay
we basically פוסקן *Pasken* that unless you do this all three at
the same time it's not an איסור כלאים issur kilayim *Issur Kilayim*
so leave the guy alone. It's מותר muttar *Mutar*. Now how do
we actually פוסקן *Pasken* about this? So the other question also is
is about one minute if you just the that's כלאי הכרם kilai
hakerem *Kilay Hakerem* but how about כלאי זרעים kilai zrayim *Kilay Zeraim*?
Like there's also there's two איסורים issurim *Issurim*. One is כלאים kilayim
*Kilayim* in the vineyard where the actual produce is אסור בהנאה assur
b'hana'ah, *Assur Be'hana'ah*. And the other is כלאים Kilayim *Kilayim* not in
the vineyard where the produce is not אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah *Assur
Be'hana'ah* and one could even ask whether the produce is like אסור
assur *Assur* at all.
So the question is but it's certainly אסור assur *Assur* to do.
But the question here is well why isn't this at least אסור
assur *Assur* the wheat and the barley if he's throwing it in
the vineyard maybe it's not כלאי הכרם kilai hakerem *Kilay Hakerem* but
let it at least be כלאי זרעים kilai zrayim. *Kilay Zeraim* right
let it be because it's two seeds together. So תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot*
goes through this whole discussion and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says the following.
He says and there's two things כלאי זרעים kilai zrayim *Kilay Zeraim*
and כלאי הכרם kilai hakerem *Kilay Hakerem*. Like what are the two
פסוקים *Pesukim*?
Because the תורה Torah, *Torah* says שדך לא תזרע כלאים sadcha lo
tizra kilayim. *Sadcha lo tizra kilayim*. And it says
what's the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*? לא תזרע כרמך karmecha, כלאים Kilayim פן
תקדש המלאה pen tikdash hamle'ah *Lo tizra carmecha kilayim pen tikdash hamaleiah*.
So by the כלאי *Kilay* by the כלאי הכרם kilai hakerem *Kilay
Hakerem* it says פן תקדש המלאה *pen tikdash hamaleiah* that the produce
is forbidden. It doesn't say it by the by the by the
כלאי זרעים kilai zrayim *Kilay Zeraim*. So there's two issues here. So
actually it's a good point to stop and to clarify that. So
first let's take a look at what תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says. He
says
if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot לא קיימא לן *Tosafot
Lo Kayma Lan* so first go about six lines in where it
says עד כאן לשונו *ad kan leshono* at the beginning of the
line. He says ונראה דהא דבעי רבי יאשיה חטה ושעורה וחרצן היינו
דוקא להתחייב משום כלאי הכרם kilai hakerem. אבל מכלאי זרעים מתחייב משני
מינים כמו חטה ושעורה *ve'nir'eh de'ha de'ba'ei Rabbi Yoshiya chittah u'se'orah ve'chartzan
hainu davka lehischayev mishum kilay hakerem aval mikilay zeraim mis-chayev mishnei minim
kemo chittah u'se'orah*. Okay so two so obviously then all three is
only כלאי הכרם kilai hakerem: *Kilay Hakerem*. So now the question is
why not put him in חרם *Cherem* because he puts the חטה
*Chittah* and the שעורה *Se'orah* in the vineyard. So if you skip
later in תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* תוספות *Tosafot* says like this he
says
one minute
ואם תאמר *ve'im tomar*. Okay one minute no no that okay well
first of all this is an interesting read of the פסוק *Pasuk*.
So go about 10 lines before the 15 lines before the end
of the of the long line get-one in תוספות *Tosafot* line starts
with the word כלאי זרעים kilai zrayim *Kilay Zeraim*. He says ואם
תאמר אמאי לא בעי רבי יאשיה בכלאי זרעים אלא ella, שני מינים
ובכלאי הכרם בעי שלשה מינים *ve'im tomar amai lo ba'ei Rabbi Yoshiya
be'kilay zeraim ela shenei minim u've'kilay hakerem ba'ei sheloshah minim*? What's the
logic? So this listen to this nice read of the פסוק *Pasuk*.
ויש לומר דמשמע ליה דקרא הכי קאמר *ve'yesh lomar de'mashma leh di'kra
hachi ka'amar*. כרמך לא תזרע כלאים karmecha lo tizra kilayim, כלומר דבעינן
שיהיו כלאים קודם שיבואו בכרם. kol lomar d'iba'inan she'yehu kila'im kodem she'yavo
b'kerem. So it says before you actually come into the כרם kerem
you have to create the כלאים in your hand, you have to
have כלאים which is חיטה ושעורה chita u'se'ora together with כרמך, karmecha,
together with the grapevine. אבל גבי שדך וכלאי זרעים כגון חיטה ושעורה
קריא כלאים מדיחיש שזרען בקרקע דהגופא קרי קרקע קרי שדה. Aval gabei
sadcha v'kilai zrayim kegon chita u'se'ora kriya kilayim m'dichayish she'zora'an b'karka d'hagufe
kari karka kari sadeh. So he basically says if it says שדך
לא תזרע כלאים, tizra kilayim, he says something is a שדה sadeh
without being... I'm still trying to get the... something is somehow a
שדה... sadeh... it exists...
it's just a field. So תזרע כלאים, you put the two seeds
in the field. Whereas כרמך לא תזרע כלאים, it's not a כרם,
kerem, it's not a vineyard unless you're dealing already with the grapes.
It's a שדה sadeh by itself, but it's only a כרם kerem
if you're dealing with the grapes. So you have to have your
כלאים and you have to have your כרמך, so you have your
two other grains plus your plus your wine plus your grape seed.
Now ונראה דהלכה כרבי אושעיא... v'nira d'halakha k'Rabbi Oshaya... דדווקא... davka... so
we rule like רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. Now how about the חוץ
לארץ chutz la'aretz issue? He says like this. He says ומותר, u'mutar,
look at the first wide line of תוספות, ומותר לזרוע תחת הכרם
u'mutar lizroa tachat hakerem as long because as long as you can
actually plant כלאים with your vineyard as long as you didn't plant
them all together at the same time. וגם מותר לזרוע כלאי זרעים
בחוץ לארץ כמאן דהכא רב יוסף מרי בזיוני וזרע. V'gam mutar lizroa
kilai zrayim b'chutz la'aretz k'man d'hacha Rav Yosef marei bizyonei v'zareh. Okay
actually we're not up to yet that. Okay, so anyway so תוספות
says so first of all yes there is separate things about כלאי
זרעים kilay zeraim and כלאי הכרם kilai hakerem. but and but anyway
but this is the position of רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya and he
says that we פסקן pasken like רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. I do
have to say that it's not clear to me that if you're
planting wheat and barley and you're throwing it in a vineyard why...
I get why it's not כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem but isn't that
just סתם כלאי זרעים? stam kilai zrayim? That is not so clear
to me. It's not a שדה sadeh anyway, maybe the fact
that it's a
כרם kerem takes it out of שדך לא תזרע כלאים. That's interesting.
Anyway he said don't go ahead and put them in חרם. We
have a very very limited definition of what the act of איסור
issur כלאים is. In חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz. Well that's not clear.
Maybe even not in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz? but certainly in חוץ
לארץ, chutz la'aretz, okay? So now let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara
Or pot it would be
okay.
Okay,
so let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, now רב יוסף מרי
בזיוני וזרע. Rav Yosef m'arei bizyonei v'zareh. רב יוסף Rav Yosef would
mix seeds and plant them. So that sounds like and רש"י Rashi
says
ולא בכרם. v'lo b'kerem. So רש"י Rashi he's living in חוץ... chutz...
so not in a vineyard. So the question is if you plant
it like Michael said in a vineyard ironically, paradoxically, that would take
him out of... that would be in the כלאי כרם kilai kerem
category and it would not be חייב chayiv because you didn't plant
the grape seed at the same time. But if you're planting two
seeds out of a vineyard in a field then that should be
enough to at least be כלאי זרעים. kilay zeraim So let's take
a look. אמר אביי ואנן תנן הכלאים מדברי סופרים. Amar Abaye v'anan
tnan hakilayim midivrei sofrim. Okay and don't tell me any רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya here 'cause it's not a vineyard and you're planting two
seeds at the same time. אמר ליה לא קשיא כאן בכלאי כרם
כאן בכלאי זרעים. Amar lei lo kashya, kan b'kilai kerem kan b'kilai
zrayim. So no, כלאי זרעים kilay zeraim doesn't apply in חוץ לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, only כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem applies in
חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Okay. כלאי כרם דבארץ אסורים בהנאה בחוץ לארץ
נמי גזרו רבנן. Kilai kerem d'b'aretz assurim b'hana'ah, b'chutz la'aretz nami gazru
rabanan. כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem. which is very weighty that in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael not only are you not allowed to do it
but the produce is forbidden and forbidden אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, that
we applied in חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz, כלאי זרעים דבארץ לא אסרי
רבנן, Kilai zrayim d'b'aretz lo assri rabanan, כלאי זרעים kilay zeraim which
is never אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah.
even in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, בחוץ לארץ נמי לא גזרו בהו
רבנן. b'chutz la'aretz nami lo gazru bahu rabanan. The rabbis weren't גוזר.
gozer. So all this teaching we've been saying that כלאיים kilayim is
אסור assur in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz. he would say is limited
to כלאי הכרם. kilay hakerem. So listen to how much we've narrowed
it. By the way, remember the משנה Mishna talked about buying vegetables
outside of a vineyard. You remember the משנה Mishna about the כלאיים
kilayim specifically discussed a vineyard? Okay, so anyway so he is saying
the only thing אסור assur in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz. is food...
is planting, you know, two seeds together with a grape seed. You
can plant two seeds in a vineyard, you can plant two seeds
elsewhere, the only thing אסור assur, is the רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya
version of כלאי הכרם: kilay hakerem, planting those three types of seed
together. That's the only thing אסור assur in חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz,
Everything else you're totally fine.
And כלאי זרעים
kilay
zeraim in חוץ chutz, לארץ?
Just what we just said, would not apply. The only thing אסור
assur, is כלאי הכרם.
kilay hakerem, At the same time.
At the same time, you can even plant two seeds in a
vineyard.
And then add it later? Exactly.
So אמר רב יוסף רב מודי דמי... Amar Rav Yosef: rav modei
demi... but then רב יוסף Rav Yosef backs off. No no, what
I said isn't
true. רב זירא גינתא דבי רב, d'Rav Zeira ginsa d'bei Rav, רב
planted a garden for the... owned by like the ישיבה... yeshiva... okay,
apparently there was a garden that they would have to provide for
the food for the ישיבה בחורים... yeshiva bachurim... okay, מישרי מישרי meishari
meishari and he did different rows. Each row in the garden would
be a different vegetable. So and he would not mix them up.
מאי טעמא לאו משום עירוב עירובי כלאים? Mai ta'ama lav mishum iruv
iruvei kilayim? Isn't it because he didn't want to mix them
up because...
Had he planted it in a way which would have demonstrated that
he wanted them near, but he was like there's a way you
can plant, like you plant four rows like this, there's
a whole פרק, perek,
I know, and then you plant one thing, if he had done
something like that which clearly was manipulating it in a way to
avoid כלאים problems, it would have shown us that he holds of
כלאי זרעים kilay zeraim in חוץ לארץ, okay? But אלא הכא משום
נוי, ela hacha mishum noy,
maybe here he just did, you know, just for aesthetics. You don't
want to mix the stuff up. You want one row of broccoli
and one row of cauliflower and whatever. ואינמי משום טרחא דשמעיה, v'inami
mishum tircha dashamaia,
or just because of the effort of the attendant. He says, you
know, we need some tomatoes for today's salad, so all the tomatoes
are in the same place. Of course you want your garden organized.
Who says that it's for a halachic reason? So by the end
of the day, we said anyway, in terms of eating the produce,
you can basically turn a blind eye and create ספקות, sfeikot, different
levels maybe. And in terms of actually doing it, okay, that by
the תוספות at least פוסק by, he thinks the conclusion of the
גמרא Gemara is כלאי זרעים kilay zeraim does not apply at all
in חוץ לארץ, only כלאי הכרם kilay hakerem and only in the
רבי יאשיה version. So he's extremely limited, like the scope right of
all of this. Okay, so anyway, so let me just actually just
one second because
of all that בבל, Bavel, of all
that, well, yeah, I mean, I don't think for example, I don't
think רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan would have been happy about any of
this. Okay, so anyway,
one minute.
Yeah, that'll have
a big impact.
Just one second.
They
didn't have broccoli.
Now in terms of the what do you call it, in terms
of the question about about what is אסור, assur because the, you
know, the גמרא Gemara here uses the phrase that כלאי הכרם kilay
hakerem, is אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, כלאי זרעים kilay zeraim is not
אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. But actually in the תורה, Torah it never
says that כלאי זרעים kilay zeraim is אסור assur at all.
It only says פן תקדש המלאה by כלאי הכרם.
kilay hakerem, You mean אסור, assur just check what
you mean to eat, perhaps?
Yeah. רמב"ם, Rambam for example, wait, in the רמב"ם Rambam in מאכלות
אסורות, Ma'achalos Assuros, he only mentions כלאי הכרם. Kilay Hakerem, כלאי הכרם,
Kilay Hakerem the רמב"ם says, hold on, in פרק י"ג Perek Yud
Gimmel in מאכלות אסורות, Ma'achalos Assuros, he says, here. Here. ויש אסורים
מהם של תורה בזרע הארץ והם החדש וכלאי
הכרם והטבל
והערלה. V'yesh assurim mehem
shel
Torah b'zera ha'aretz v'hen hachadash v'kilay hakerem v'hatevel
v'ha'orla.
So
although the גמרא Gemara, is actually a little bit misleading because the
גמרא Gemara says that כלאי זרעים kilay zeraim, is not אסור בהנאה,
assur behana'ah but כלאי זרעים is not actually אסור assur at all.
And this is a real important question because you know, Dov there
was asking about like how do we eat the, you know, what
are they, nectarines and tangelos and all these types of things. So
a real important point to make is, besides what you could say,
well in the end we פוסק כלאי זרעים doesn't apply in חוץ
לארץ. So in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you can't eat, you know,
you can't eat tangerines, right? So the הלכה, I mean maybe, I
don't know, maybe they don't grow in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, maybe
they're imported. But the basic point is, is that כלאי זרעים is
only is only אסור assur, to do, not אסור assur, to eat.
The only thing that's אסור assur to eat whether in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael or in חוץ, you know, even in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael is כלאי הכרם, which is why the משנה Mishna that talked
about buying vegetables and the case of ספק talked about buying vegetables
near a vineyard. So to summarize, let's pull this all together. Okay.
ערלה Orla is אסור, assur well not the plant, the tree, but
the food is אסור assur בהנאה. Okay. כלאי הכרם in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael is אסור, assur is אסור assur, בהנאה and אסור assur
to do. כלאי זרעים in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is אסור assur
to do, but you can actually eat the produce, which means that
any type of hybrid food that does not involve a vine, any
type of hybrid food that does not involve a vine is totally
מותר mutar to eat. Outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, okay, it's
דאורייתא de'oraita אסור assur to crossbreed animals, it's דאורייתא de'oraita אסור assur
to graft a tree, okay, that does not make the fruit אסור,
assur it's דאורייתא de'oraita אסור assur to do. Okay. It's דרבנן derabbanan
אסור assur to to do כלאי הכרם, according to this גמרא, Gemara.
though, maybe only if all three seeds at once, okay, and according
to the way תוספות understands, it is not אסור assur to plant
כלאי זרעים, and there is and the only thing that would be
אסור assur to eat from all of those, it's not אסור assur
to use the produce of כלאי בהמה, kilay behemah, you can use
a mule. It's not אסור to use the produce of הרכבת האילן,
harkavat ha'ilan, you can go ahead and eat nectarines. Okay. The only
thing that is אסור is that is אסור in terms of the
produce, whether in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or in חוץ לארץ, is
כלאי הכרם, okay, and the only thing the only איסורים issurim that's
in terms of the produce, and the only איסורים to do in
חוץ לארץ. are cross-breeding animals, cross-breeding trees, that's a דאורייתא d'Oraita and
כלאי הכרם, the way תוספות conclude כלאי הכרם if you do all
three seeds at once. Yes, exactly.
What would be great? The charts. A chart, yes.
I find that shocking
that you have an איסור דאורייתא issur d'Oraita like הרכבת אילן harkavat
ilan
and
there was no גזרה אטו הרכבה gezeirah atu harkavah on an איסור
issur of the אכילה. achilah. Right. I find that like shocking.
Things you can't do without there being a consequence. Well, but according
to some ראשונים Rishonim that's why the תורה Torah forbids בשר בחלב
basar b'chalav to eat בשר בחלב basar b'chalav because it's the- there
had to be a consequence to the איסור of you having cooked
them together. You know? But- but for example by שבת, Shabbat, there's
a debate, there is an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that מעשה
שבת maaseh Shabbat is אסור דאורייתא, assur d'Oraita, but we basically פסקן
pasken it's דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. You can violate שבת Shabbat and the- the
wages of sin are not אסור in the- are not אסור מן
התורה. assur min haTorah. But here I think what bothers you is
not just that it's a produce of sin, but that conceptually the
problem of כלאים is the having brought these things together. So conceptually
the mixture of the two is problematic, right? I think- I think
you intuitively feel that more than like the produce of חילול שבת.
chilul Shabbat. I understand that. Okay. Yes.
So when we say it's actually אסור just the כלאים would be
like literally plant them, but if I'm genetically engineering it, is that
something, is that something completely different? So it would be מותר even
for me to do that?
Yeah, like in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. I mean to- what- create
a seed that has- yeah, I presumably, yes. Yeah.
One mention in the סוגיא sugya is that בית דין Beit Din
actually go into people's fields and destroy.
Right. Correct. Okay. Let's move on to the next משנה. mishna. This
actually is a nice little aggadic break, and, you know, and whatever,
let's take a look. כל העושה מצוה אחת מטיבין לו ומאריכין לו
ימיו ונוחל את הארץ. Kol ha'oseh mitzvah achat metivin lo u'ma'arichin lo
yamav v'nochel et ha'aretz. Anybody does just one מצוה, mitzvah, good is
done to you and you have long life and you inherit the
land, which presumably means, I don't know, עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, although
again we were just talking in the context of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and חוץ לארץ. So I'm serious, נוחל את הארץ nochel et
ha'aretz is clearly picking up on that theme, but whether it's meant
metaphorically, literally, or just, you know, literarily to pick up on that
theme. Okay. I know, but we're saying כל מצוה, kol mitzvah, כל
העושה מצוה, kol ha'oseh mitzvah, it's always כל, kol, right? You know,
you know כל מצוות האב על הבן, kol mitzvot ha'av al ha'ben,
כל מצוות הבן על האב, kol mitzvot ha'ben al ha'av, you know
כל מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמה, kol mitzvot aseh she'hazman gerama, כל מצוות
עשה שאין הזמן גרמה, kol mitzvot aseh she'ein hazman gerama, כל המצוות
התלויות בארץ, kol hamitzvot hateluyot baaretz, and now it's כל העושה מצוה.
kol ha'oseh mitzvah. So we're talking until now about categorizing מצוות, mitzvot,
right, מצוות mitzvot of men, מצוות mitzvot of women, ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, חוץ לארץ, and now we're talking about anybody- what it means
the power of performing a מצוה mitzvah is, even one מצוה, mitzvah,
the power of performing it, but we're using the same literary structure
of כל kol and מצוה. mitzvah. And we're also picking up on
the theme of ארץ aretz even though here presumably ארץ aretz means
עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. Okay. וכל שאינו עושה מצוה אחת אין מטיבין
לו ואין מאריכין לו ימיו ואינו נוחל את הארץ. V'chol she'eino oseh
mitzvah achat ein metivin lo v'ein ma'arichin lo yamav v'eino nochel et
ha'aretz. Obviously, people will realize that there's a little bit of a
problem here because people can do one מצוה mitzvah and not do
another מצוה, mitzvah, and then what do you get? Do you get
אריכות ימים arichut yamim or do you not get אריכות ימים? arichut
yamim? So anyway, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara רמינו.
Raminu. The גמרא Gemara, says this seems to say that any מצוה
mitzvah you will reap the rewards in this world, right? That's the
point of מטיבין לו. metivin lo. But I'll ask you on this:
אלו דברים שאדם אוכל פירותיהם בעולם הזה והקרן קיימת לו לעולם הבא.
Eilu devarim she'adam ochel peiroteihem ba'olam hazeh v'hakeren kayemet lo l'olam haba.
Look, they took this right out of the סידור. Siddur. No, it's
from the משנה, mishna, first משנה mishna in פאה. Pe'ah. Okay, אלו
הן. eilu hein. So here are the מצוות mitzvot that you reap
the rewards in this- in this world: כיבוד אב ואם וגמילות חסדים
והכנסת אורחים והבאת שלום בין אדם לחברו ותלמוד תורה כנגד כולם. Kibbud
av v'em v'gemilut chasadim v'hachnasat orchim v'hava'at shalom bein adam l'chavero v'talmud
torah kineged kulam. Now, I just want to pause for a moment.
Yes, apparently there's a question about that גרסא. girsa. Okay, now by
the way, also הכנסת אורחים hachnasat orchim is not in the משנה,
mishna, and besides that- right, anyway, so there's questions of the גרסא,
girsa, but I want to point out something here. It is very
possible to read this משנה mishna
of אוכל פירותיהם בעולם הזה ochel peiroteihem ba'olam hazeh to mean not
that God will reward you, but that the very reality of these
מצוות mitzvot you will experience the benefits of them in this world,
right, in a very pragmatic way, right? I mean, if you think
about it, if you honor your parents, there is some real, you
know, not necessarily that that means your parents will be nicer to
you, I don't know what it will do to the quality of
your life, to your relationship with your- your
kids
will see it and they'll honor you, and especially when you get
right- these other things, you do kindness to other people, you know,
a, it could be reciprocated and b, also just what that does
for you. I mean, there was- I just recently saw a TED
talk that it was- they did a study and they- and they
showed that when you do- like, like your degree of happiness, they
gave everybody like- they did this study, they gave people twenty dollars
or forty dollars a week and they said you have to spend
it. And on one group they said you have to spend it
on yourself, and to another group they said that you have to
spend it to- to- for somebody else. And then they did ways
of testing their, I don't know, their happiness and satisfaction quotient and
whatever. Anyway, the people who spent it on other people were like
had a much greater degree of happiness and satisfaction than the- the
people who spent it on themselves. So anyway, so there's real ways
in which you can see that this is like not just God
will reward you. These are the types of מצוות mitzvos that you
can see the concrete benefits of them in this world. Anyway, but
the גמרא'ס Gemara's reading it as, it sounds like other מצוות mitzvos
you shouldn't expect any reward in this world. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so how do you reconcile this? אמר רב יהודה הכי קאמר,
Amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar, here's how you read it. כל עושה
מצוה אחת יתירה על זכיותיו מטיבין לו. Kol oseh mitzvah achas yeseira
al zechuyosav meitivin lo. No, no, no, it doesn't mean you get
the reward for this מצוה. mitzvah. It means if you basically are
fifty-fifty, your merits and your demerits, and this מצוה mitzvah is added
onto the scale, okay, and it then you've tipped the scale into
your in your favor, then in that case, where were we, מטיבין
לו ודומה כמי שמקיים כל התורה כולה. meitivin lo ve-domeh ke-mi she-mekayem
kol ha-Torah kullah. Then they do good to you and it's like
you fulfilled the entire תורה Torah. cause now you're on the side
of the positive. By the way, that helps explain, yeah, exactly, the
whole thing about fifty-fifty and the רמב"ם in תשובה, Teshuvah, it's a
גמרא, Gemara anyway, completely reframes the issue. But by the way, it
helps explain the משנה mishnah that the משנה mishnah isn't a contradiction,
because now we're talking about somebody that's fifty-fifty. So if you do
one thing to tip the scales in your favor, or if you
don't do one thing then it tips the scales in your detriment.
So it exactly contains the universe of, you know, two possible options.
Okay. So the גמרא gemara says, מכלל דהנך אפילו בחדא נמי? mikhlal
de-hanei afilu be-chada nami? Do you mean to tell me that these
things that are in the משנה mishnah in פאה, Peah, even one
alone, even if you're basically a רשע? rasha? Because you're saying that
now what's the difference otherwise between those things in פאה Peah and
our משנה? mishnah? Our משנה'ס mishnah's fifty-fifty, this makes you a צדיק.
tzaddik. So what's the extra power of the things in פאה? Peah?
That even if you're a רשע rasha you get that type of
reward? So the גמרא gemara says,
reward for the מצוה mitzvah you do for that מצוה, mitzvah, it
also includes those other things.
Could be. אמר רב שמיה לומר שאם היתה שקולה מכרעת. Amar Rav
Shmaya lomar she-im hayesa shekulah machra'as.
No, no, here's the difference. If you have fifty-fifty and one of
these מצוות mitzvos in פאה Peah is in your is amongst your
fifty percent of good deeds, then it's like you have fifty-one percent.
A little bit more. Then it's a little weightier. You don't need
an extra thing to tip the scale. If that's not in your
good deeds, then that's our משנה mishnah that you need one more
מצוה mitzvah to tip the scale. Again, it's really completely reframing the
issues to the case in which it's like
things are on the scale.
But also to the way in which it's so, I don't know,
you know, technical
and accounting and it applies only in rare cases, it's like it's
not nearly as satisfying to read. Right. From the power of what
one מצוה mitzvah means. וכל עושה מצוה אחת יתירה על זכיותיו. Ve-kol
oseh mitzvah achas yeseira al zechuyosav. So if you have it's in
your fifty percent and you have one of the משנה mishnah things
in פאה, Peah, then you're in the positive side. If you don't
have one of the things in פאה Peah but you do one
more, then מטיבין לו. meitivin lo. Fine. All right, that was not
so satisfying. ורמיניהו, Ve-ramineihu, I'll ask you on this. כל שזכיותיו מרובין
מעונותיו מריעין לו ודומה כמי ששרף כל התורה כולה. Kol she-zechuyosav merubin
me-avonosav me-arin lo ve-domeh ke-mi she-saraf kol ha-Torah kullah.
Now we have a more bigger sort of theological question. Because we
have a teaching that says the exact opposite of what you would
have expected. That if you actually are somebody that's a בינוני, beinoni,
but you're a little bit on the plus side. So what God
wants, okay, fine, you're not a צדיק גמור, tzaddik gamur, okay, fine,
you're a little on the plus side, but you got a lot
of עבירות, aveiros, God wants to help you clean your slate for
עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba. So you're going to suffer a lot in
this world. This is obviously the classic way in which the rabbis
dealt with צדיק ורע לו. tzaddik ve-ra lo. God is going to
make you suffer. Sorry. God is going to make I meant the
problem of צדיק... tzaddik... anyway, God is going to make you suffer
in this world to clean your slate for the world to come.
Okay. כל שזכיותיו מרובין מעונותיו Kol she-zechuyosav merubin me-avonosav
but you got עונות, avonos, מריעין לו, me-arin lo, it's done it
you suffer. ודומה כמי ששרף כל התורה כולה. Ve-domeh ke-mi she-saraf kol
ha-Torah kullah.
It's like you burnt the תורה. Torah You'll have such such suffering
that it'll seem like you've done the most unimaginable sin. ולא השאיר
ממנו אפילו אות אחת, Ve-lo hiyara mimmenu afilu osa achas, it'll look
like what you would expect from somebody who did not do even
one מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so that's a way of explaining why a
good person suffers. Yes, that's what it's going to look like, like
somebody who didn't do any מצוות, mitzvos, but ultimately it's to clean
their slate. Okay. וכל שעונותיו מרובין מזכיותיו, Ve-chol she-avonosav merubin mi-zechuyosav,
but if you have more sins than benefits, מטיבין לו ודומה כמי
שקיים כל התורה
כולה. meitivin lo ve-domeh ke-mi she-kiyyem kol ha-Torah kullah. It'll look like
you this person will have so much good
fortune, it'll look like he's the biggest צדיק. tzaddik. And you say
how could it be, he's a רשע. rasha. That's what it's going
to look like for the רשע rasha in order that he should
get paid up in this world and suffer in the world to
come. ולא חיסר אות אחת ממנו. Ve-lo chisar osa achas mimmenu. So
that's a nice way of proactively addressing the צדיק ורע לו tzaddik
ve-ra lo problem, but it goes against our משנה. mishnah. Because our
משנה mishnah says if you do מצוות mitzvos you get rewarded. So
how do you deal with that? Okay. So אמר אביי מתניתין דעבדין
ליה יום טוב ויום ביש. Amar Abaye Masnisin de-avdin leh yom tov
ve-yom bish. So Abaye says here's the answer. And the way רש"י
has one way of reading it but I'm going to read it
תוספות'ס Tosafot's way, it's a much nicer way. He says Abaye says
look, basically if you're a צדיק tzaddik you'll have it good in
this world. But some days it'll look like you will suffer as
much as the biggest רשע. rasha. There will be some days some
days of suffering, and if you're a רשע, rasha, you'll have it
bad in this world, but there will be some days that you'll
have a good day and you'll have a lot of fortune, so
read this משנה mishna of saying all this negative stuff for the
צדיק tzadik and all of this positive stuff for the רשע, rasha,
that's not your overall life. Those are individual days will look like
that, okay, but over on the balance, if you're a צדיק tzadik
you'll have it good and if you're a רשע rasha you'll have
it bad. It'd be nice if things worked out that way. רבא
אמר הא מני הא מני Rava amar ha mani ha mani רבי
יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov.
No no no, the ברייתא braita that teaches that it'll be the
opposite of your merits, that you don't get rewarded in this world,
it doesn't reflect your deeds in this world, that's רבי יעקב Rabbi
Yaakov because רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says that all of the reward
is for the world to come and it's not reflected in this
world. דאמר שכר מצוה בהאי עלמא ליכא. de-ammar sechar mitzvah be-hai alma
lekka. It's such a nice little punchy phrase. I mean this is
high, big theology here. Don't expect any reward in this world. The
reward for the מצוות mitzvos is all going to be in the
world to come. So our משנה mishna holds you do get reward
in this world, and רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov holds no, this world
the צדיקים tzadikim will suffer, all the reward will be in the
world to come.
Meaning as that suggests before that like with good...
yeah, it'll be like the person who was סורא כותא כותא, sora
kusa kusa, that's רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. He says any reward you
get will be in the world to come, this world expect you
can easily expect suffering. דתניא רבי יעקב אומר אין לך כל מצוה
ומצוה שכתובה בתורה שמתן שכרה בצדה שאין תחיית המתים תלויה בה. detanya
Rabbi Yaakov omer ein le-cha kol mitzvah u-mitzvah she-kesuvah ba-torah she-mattan secharah
be-tziddah she-ein techiyas hamessim teluyah bah. And you don't have any מצוה
mitzvah in the תורה Torah. where it says you'll be rewarded where
it's not really referring to תחיית המתים, techiyas hamessim, not this world.
Don't expect it in this world. Okay, בכיבוד אב כתיב למען יאריכון
ימיך ולמען ייטב לך, bekibbud av kesiv lema-an yaarichun yamecha u-le-ma-an yitav
lach, it seems like it'll be great for you in this world.
בשילוח הקן כתיב למען ייטב לך והארכת ימים. beshilluach haken kesiv lema-an
yitav lach ve-ha-arachta yamim.
But now here's the problem. הרי שאמר לו אביו עלה לבירה, ha-rei
she-amar lo aviv aleh la-birah, imagine someone said to his son, go
up to that castle, to that tower, והבא לי גוזלות, ve-havi li
gozalos, and bring me down the chicks, ועלה לבירה ve-alah la-birah he
went there, ושלח את האם ve-shillach es ha-em he sent away the
mother bird, ונטל את הבנים ve-natal es habbanim and he took the
chicks, ובחזרתו נפל ומת. u-bechaziraso nafal ve-mess. Let's say he had a
tragedy. He says come on, you know you go out and you
look in the world and things don't work the way they're supposed
to work in the תורה. Torah Okay, somebody did the two מצוות
mitzvos that's supposed to be הארכת ימים harachas yamim and he died
at a tragic young age. היכן טובת ימיו של זה והיכן אריכות
ימיו של זה? heichen tovas yamav shel zeh ve-heichen arichas yamav shel
zeh?
So how do you deal with צדיק ורע לו? tzadik ve-ra lo?
How do you deal with the fact that the תורה Torah makes
promises and it doesn't seem to come true? So this is like
asking the biggest theological question. אלא, the answer is, it all has
to be in עולם הבא. olam haba. למען ייטב לך lema-an yitav
lach to be good לעולם שכולו טוב le-olam she-kullo tov in the
world that's all good, ולמען יאריכון ימיך u-lema-an yaarichun yamecha לעולם שכולו
ארוך. le-olam she-kullo aroch. Okay, so he puts all of the reward
in the world to come. He is the one that the ברייתא
braita teaches the צדיקים tzadikim will suffer. Our משנה mishna teaches no
you will be rewarded in this world.
And
you could remember משנה mishna too says... I don't...
you could, you could, but לעולם שכולו ארוך... le-olam she-kullo aroch... and
you could, you could, but no it doesn't sound like that. מטיבין
לו metivin lo sounds like here. Anyway, let's just read one more
line. והגמרא ve-hagemara says first of all ודילמא לאו הכי הוה, ve-dilma
lav hachi havah, maybe how can you be bringing a proof from
an imagined scenario? Maybe that never happened. Maybe everybody who listened to
their father really really...
you know it's a theoretical case, he is examining this ברכה. bracha.
Right, but no but you can't use it to challenge a פסוק.
Maybe it always happened that people who honored their parents lived long
days. So the גמרא says no רבי יעקב מעשה חזא, Rabbi Yaakov
maiseh chaza, רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov he saw it, he saw that
event, and therefore he says that needs explanation. הגמרא hagemara says ודילמא
מהרהר בעבירה הוה, ve-dilma meharher ba-aveirah havah, but okay, maybe the kid
when he was going up on the you know the tower was
planning on doing a sin and that's why he died. So the
גמרא says no מחשבה רעה אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מצרפה למעשה. machashavah
ra'ah ein ha-kadosh baruch hu metzarfah le-ma'aseh. God would not count a
thought of sin against a person. So that couldn't have been the
case, that's not an explanation. הגמרא hagemara says ודילמא מהרהר בעבודה זרה
הוה, ve-dilma meharher ba-avodah zarah havah, maybe he was planning on doing
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, דכתיב למען תפוס את בית ישראל בלבם, de-chesiv
le-ma'an tpos es beis yisrael be-libbam, then they'll be seized for the
even the thoughts of their heart. אי נמי הכי קאמר, ei nammi
hachi kammar, no you know what that's part of his point. אי
סלקא דעתך שכר מצוה בהאי עלמא, i-sal-ka da'atach sechar mitzvah be-hai alma,
if a person really would get reward for a מצוה mitzvah in
this
world, אמאי לא אגן מצוה עליה כי היכי דלא ליתי לידי הרהור,
ammai lo aggen mitzvah aleh ke-heichi de-lo leyessi lidei hirhur, then the
מצוה mitzvah should have protected him to have not had the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah thought, which is basically saying like give me a
break.
The real world clearly contradicts the promises in the תורה and we
have to go ahead and find another way of explaining what those
promises are about. Okay so we'll pick up with this.